So
you really don't have an option
about whether or not you're going to
develop a vision for your life.
You can either develop a
good vision or bad vision.
That's your option.
Or you can live out your vision or someone else's.
There's no no-vision option.
If you have poor vision,
immature and hedonistic,
that might be a good way of thinking about it,
then the vision that you impose on the world is
merely a consequence of your short-term whims.
You're going to be governed by something,
and you need to know that.
And there isn't much difference between
being goverened by something and being
possessed by something.
And that's a useful thing to know, too, because
if you have any sense at all,
you'd want to be possessed by the right thing,
because if you're possessed by the wrong thing,
you're going to be in so much trouble,
you can hardly imagine it.
And not only are you going to be in trouble,
you're going to be trouble
to everyone that you encounter.
And that seems like a very bad plan.
And it's not necessary.
So it would be better to do the better thing.
And so I entitled this relatively brief course,
Vision and Plan: Theory and Practice.
That's a repetitive title.
A vision is a broad theory,
and a plan is a narrow and focused vision.
And so a broad vision focuses
to a point that can be implemented.
And so what I'm going to do with you over the next
hours is
describe to you
how you might conceptualize a vision
in the broadest possible sense,
so that you understand deeply
why doing so is necessary, so
that you understand the consequences of doing it
properly and you understand
the consequences of doing it improperly.
Then we're going to take that general conceptual
scheme, and we're going to focus it down to the
point where it becomes practically implementable.
Because one of the things
you might most want to do if you become
psychologically or philosophically informed is
to understand how you take that broader
conceptualization and make it relevant
and implementable within
the confines of your own life.
Then you have the advantages of the broader
philosophical view, but also something
to do that's extraordinarily practical.
And I would say that abstract ideas become
meaningful when they're implementable.
That's a good thing to know if you're
ever talking to people
and you want to motivate them,
if you have a broad-scale vision.
Maybe you're trying to organize people
to engage in some endeavor.
That could be your family or your business
compatriots, your friends, any sort of occasion.
You want to give them the general picture,
but then you also want to be able to specify
for them exactly what they need to do.
And what they need to do is how they need
to transform the way they look at the situation
and how they need to reconstruct their actions.
And so we're going to go from the general to
the specific over the course of this discussion.
So we'll start very general.
I want to present you with a way
of conceptualizing the world of experience
in the broadest possible sense,
because that'll give you
the initial introduction into why
developing a vision is inevitable and necessary.
So this is a Daoist image of the world,
and it isn't the image that people in the West are
generally familiar with,
because we tend to think of the world as material,
but the world is not merely material,
not least because the world is at least material
and information, and information is not,
it's not material in a reductive sense.
The classic view of the world,
even in the West, was more like the Daoist view.
And the Daoist view is that
the world of your experience, and maybe even
the world as such, is made up of two components.
One, you could conceptualize as chaos,
and the other, you could conceptualize as order.
And in the yin and yang symbol,
which is two serpents, by the way, head to tail,
the black serpent is chaos,
and the white serpent is order.
And the black serpent is generally identified
with the feminine, which is not
the same as the female or the woman.
And the white serpent is
characterized as masculine.
I'll describe why that is as we progress.
So what does this mean,
that the world is chaos and order, in its,
what would you say,
initial differentiated conception?
You could think of the world of experience as
a transcendent unity, and that would be
the unity of all things.
And then you could think of that unity as
falling into pieces.
Each of us is a piece of an overarching unity.
You might ask, well, what is the most
fundamental initial breakdown of the unity?
And the answer to that is,
well, it's chaos and order.
And it's always that, no matter where you are.
And so here's a way of understanding that.
No matter where you are, there are things that are
happening that you understand,
and there are things that are happening
that you don't understand.
And the things that you understand, that's order.
That's the domain of order.
And the things that you don't understand,
that transcend your understanding,
that's the domain of chaos.
And chaos is also the domain of potential,
because in the things you don't understand is
the possibility of new knowledge,
new ways of conceptualizing the world,
and new discoveries about your own nature.
And so you can be terrified of the things that you
don't understand and you don't know,
and you can see why that might be,
because they can undermine you.
But by the same token,
in the domain of things you don't understand
is all the potential of the world.
So one of the things that you might think about
deeply is, what would be a good
rule-of-thumb attitude to have
towards the things you don't know?
And one answer to that is to be terrified
into paralysis because of the necessity for change
that an encounter with the unknown might produce.
And the other is to welcome it with open arms
because the you that might emerge as a consequence
of confrontation with what you don't know might
be much better than the you you're stuck with now.
And that's very much worth considering.
How you conceptualize
the stance you take in relationship to the domains
of chaos and order, that's about the most
important decision you ever make.
If you're a tyrant, for example, you're going
to be allied 100% with what you already know.
Right?
Now, the price you pay for that is
that you forego transformation.
Another price you pay for that is,
if you're tyrannical in your alliance with what
you already understand, you're going
to attempt to force that on other people.
And part of the reason you do that is because you
don't have enough faith in your own ability
to confront what you don't understand and change.
It's not wise unless, well, I suppose you could
envision a situation where you
should only abide by what you know.
And I would say, if your life is absolutely
perfect in all of its manifestations
and you couldn't dream of having
anything better, then you can
stick with what you've got.
But if it isn't,
then there's always the possibility
that a little more transformation
on your part might be a good thing.
Right.
Now, there's a deep level of conceptualization
that goes along with that, too, which is,
how should you construe
the domain of possibility or potential?
And I suppose you might say that this is
a question of faith, right?
Because the future is unknown and indeterminate,
it's very difficult to make any
final decisions about its nature.
But you can make a meta-decision, you might say,
that the domain of potential,
if confronted properly, is positive,
and that you could establish a relationship
with it that would bring benefit to you.
That's really the attitude that children have
towards the world, is that they're open to
exploration and discovery within certain bounds.
That's often shattered, that naivety.
That naive openness of children
is often shattered by trauma.
And that tends to turn us into cynics.
But that doesn't mean that the attitude was
fundamentally inappropriate.
There's a Gospel statement
that makes the claim that you can't enter
the Kingdom of Heaven unless you become
like little children,
which is not the same as staying
like a little child, by the way,
and the idea there is that you should strive
to regain the attitude of open acceptance
of what's confronting you as an adult,
even if you've been hurt.
Because if you've been hurt, well,
then you could imagine that you're more afraid
of what you don't know because you've discovered
that it can undermine and destroy you, devour you.
And it's very easy to become cynical and bitter
and rigid as a consequence of that.
But as I said before,
the price you pay for that is that you forego
any further transformation,
and you tend to become a tyrant.
Well, unless you want to become a tyrant,
tyrants tend to live in hell.
So I wouldn't recommend it
unless that's what you want.
And you can be a tyrant to yourself just
like you're a tyrant to other people.
And in fact, that's usually a precondition
for being a tyrant to other people,
which is also a good reason not to be a tyrant
to other people, because you will
bring that attitude towards yourself.
OK, so what have we established?
Well,
we've established that you can
think about your world of experience as
bifurcated into two fundamental realms.
There's the realm of things you don't understand.
You think about that as unexplored territory.
If you want to make it more biological,
animals have to deal with a territory that they
have mastered and understand—
that's their home territory—
and they have to deal with territories
where the predators lurk, let's say.
And animals tend to stick to their home territory
because that's explored,
and they tend to be afraid of their
unexplored territory because
that's where they can be destroyed.
And so this notion,
this metaphysical notion that experience is
characterized by chaos and order,
is also a notion that
can align with a materialistic view of the world
and the psyche as a biological phenomenon.
Your nervous system is set up, really,
to respond with security when you're
in the territory that you understand
and to respond with, first,
fear and then curiosity when you encounter
the territory you don't understand.
Now, for animals, that territory tends to be
more specifically geographical, because, like,
a wolf pack will have its territory or any
given animal will have its physical territory.
Now, we inhabit a physical territory,
which is why, hopefully,
you're comfortable at home and less comfortable
when you make a foray out into the world
to places that you don't know.
But our environment is also conceptual,
and so our conceptual environments are also
divided up into the things we understand
and the things that we don't understand.
And even though we can be at home in our physical
territory and quite secure
in our metaphysical territories,
there are still domains that we don't understand,
edges and frontiers.
And so if you, maybe you have some
primitive understanding of physics,
but you could certainly
appreciate very rapidly that there are
physical theories,
theories developed by sophisticated physicists,
that transcend your understanding.
And you could imagine that there's also a place
between your understanding and those more
sophisticated theories where
you can almost understand.
And you could imagine standing on that edge
of almost understanding and being curious
and intrigued and enticed by the possibility
that you might expand your knowledge.
Well,
you're surrounded by a metaphysical territory,
a multidimensional metaphysical territory,
made of all these different domains of knowledge,
and you have some mastery over each of them.
There are elements of them that transcend you,
and there are frontiers and borders that you
could stand on where you would learn.
Here's the thing to know.
You get interested in something when
you're put on the edge of what you know.
That grip of interest is actually a manifestation
of the instinct that drives you to learn.
And you can see now and then that you'll encounter
a book or a talk or a discussion that
maximizes your engagement,
and the maximization of that engagement is
generally a signal that you're in the place where
optimized learning is taking place.
Now, people make the claim,
especially in the modern world,
that life is intrinsically meaningless,
and that's usually a rationalist claim.
I can talk about that later.
But I'm making a phenomenological claim,
which is that there's an instinct of meaning
that signals that you're in a place that's
the border between what you know and what you
don't know, that grips you,
and that that phenomenological meaning is a signal
of transformation and of expansion of adaptation.
And in consequence, it's not something that should
be eradicable by a kind of brainless nihilism.
It's actually the deepest signal you have
that you're in the place that you should be,
if you're transforming into the next
best version of yourself.
So you don't want to forego a relationship
with that, because if you do that,
because you're nihilistic, let's say,
and maybe because you've been hurt,
then you're going to destroy your relationship
with the process that could transform you
and allow you to adapt to the world.
That seems like a bad idea.
And so it's useful.
People say that they can't live without meaning.
And that's a very strange thing to say if you
think about meaning as something
that's only abstracted or metaphysical.
But if you understand
that meaning is actually a manifestation of the
instinct that signals optimal learning or optimal
transformation, then you can understand why you
might die without meaning, because in some sense,
if you're static, you're not living.
And if you also understand that meaning is
the signal of optimized transformation,
if you really understand that,
then you're immune in some ways to the
corrosive nihilism that says,
"at its core, life has no meaning."
It's like,
I probably figured this out years ago when I was
thinking about music,
because music has the aspect of intrinsic meaning.
If you're listening to a piece of music
that compels you or that you love,
and someone taps you on the shoulder and
tells you that
in the final analysis that nothing you do has any
significance, if you have any sense,
you're going to just push them away and say,
yeah, but I'm listening to the music.
And music is a balance between chaos and order.
It has an element of predictability.
Otherwise, you can't follow the piece of music,
but it has an element of unpredictability because
if it just repeats over and over,
you get bored with it very quickly.
So what a musician does is present you
with a structure of order
and then vary that in an interesting way within
a certain set of parameters
and captures your interest as a consequence.
And the reason that you feel that as meaningful is
because what music is doing is modeling
the way the world actually works.
And so that's also extremely useful to know.
You hear that music is a non-representational art,
but that's actually not true.
It's the most representational art because
it specifies most precisely
that the world is made out of order and chaos,
and that meaning is the appropriate
balance between the two.
And so I would say, if you're conducting your life
properly, so to speak,
it'll have a musical element.
It'll have that same kind of meaning
and the things will fall into place
in a relatively musical manner.
You'll see in your life that there are times when
you're in the right place at the right time,
doing the right thing, and things
fall into alignment all around you.
Temporally, they're timed well, and things seem to
exist in a harmonious relationship to one another.
And those are the times of your life that
you would like to have more of,
if you could only figure out how to do it.
And well, partly what we're going to do
in the next hours or so is see if we can step
through understanding how you might manage that.
All right. So you could say, to begin with,
the world is made out of order.
And what does it mean for things to be ordered?
There's a very specific meaning
that's useful to know about that.
You're in the domain of order when your
actions produce the outcomes you intended.
OK, so that's really what it
means to understand something.
If what you're doing produces the results that you
desire, then you're somewhere you understand.
If you're out with your friends,
hypothetically, you're there to have a good time.
If you're in a conversation with them
and the conversation is flowing smoothly,
everyone's happy and laughing, then your
emotions signal to you that the territory defined
by you and your friends and your interaction
is familiar and comfortable and promising.
It's the same thing if you have a meal
with your family and it's going well.
Now, maybe you have a meal with your family
at a vacation and someone throws something
untoward on the table,
which often happens in family gatherings.
Some unresolved issue comes up,
for one reason or another,
like it might habitually.
That's the emergence of unexplored territory into
the domain of what's predictable and positive.
And that produces all sorts of emotional
reactions, often negative,
especially if it happens involuntarily.
So that's another way of starting to understand
what it means to see the world in this way.
So you have what you understand,
which is the domain that you inhabit when your
patterns of attention and action are producing
the desired outcome,
and you have the domain of the unexpected,
and then you have the border between them as well.
So that's a good way
of conceptualizing the world as such.
And my proposition was that you experience
the positive meaning that lightens up your life
when you're standing on the border
between order and chaos.
That's the border of optimized transformation.
Because you might say you're
best situated when you're firmly
in the domain of what you understand.
That's what people think
when they pursue security.
But the problem with security is that it
has no element of transformation.
And so you don't only want to be where
things are going the way you want them to go.
You want to be where things are going the way you
want them to go,
but where you're changing and things are
changing so that they can get better.
So it's an edge.
You're not in the domain of the predictable.
You have one foot in the domain of the predictable
and another foot in the domain of the unknown,
so that you can make more of yourself
while you're sufficiently safe.
And that's why,
that's what you do when you play, by the way.
When you play, you manifest a set
of skills that you've already mastered.
Otherwise, you don't know how to play the game,
but you want to play the game on the edge.
That's why you pick a partner in a play about,
that's a challenge to you.
Because you might think, well,
if you're playing with someone,
why not just pick someone that you can beat
hands down 100% of the time?
And your answer would be, well, that's no fun.
And the question about that is, well,
why is it no fun if the aim of the game is to win?
Why not pick a partner that you
can beat 100% of the time?
Because then you win.
And the answer is, in the pursuit of that narrow,
certain victory, you forego the possibility
of becoming a better player.
Right. OK.
So there's a meaning in security, which is that
you can predict everything that's going to happen.
And there's a meaning in the unknown,
which is that you're put off your,
what would you say, you're thrown off your feet
and you're surprised and threatened and anxious.
And then there's a meaning on the border between
those where you're secure enough so that you're
stable, but you're transforming enough so
that you're moving towards an optimized
version of yourself and the world.
OK, so what we're going to do
is to detail out the processes by which you
develop the vision that enables
you to stand on that edge.
That's the plan.
All right.
Now, we live in time.
We live in space, obviously.
We inhabit our different territories,
but we also live in time.
And the entire expanse of time is also
characterized by this relationship
between the known and the unknown.
Here's an example.
You may have memories that come to visit you
of past troubles,
and those will come on you involuntarily.
And when they do, they make you anxious.
They take the foundation out
from underneath your feet.
And the degree to which they do that is
proportionate to how serious the
chasm that you encountered.
It's proportionate to the depth of the chasm
that you encountered in the past.
If you have experiences that hurt you,
that you don't understand and didn't master
and could still disturb you in the future,
then those visions, those visions
of the past will come to haunt you.
They'll haunt your nightmares.
They'll haunt your daydreams.
They'll destabilize you.
You'll be tempted to push them away.
And what that is,
the reason that that happens is because your
psyche is set up so that if you fell into a hole
once and you don't know why,
the more instinctual parts of you are going
to presume that that danger still lurks
in the future and will re-present those
experiences to you in the hope of motivating you
to develop the adaptive competence necessary
so you won't fall into that hole again.
One of the things you do in therapy,
one of the things you do
with your friends and your family members or even
with yourself, if you have some wisdom,
is if someone has a problem,
you try to walk through with them why the problem
emerged,
which might have something to do
with the vagaries of the world,
because things happen to us that are
accidental and random, that are difficult
and dangerous,
but also that our misadventures may have something
to do with the improper calibration of the way
that we're looking at and
interacting with the world.
And so when you're thinking about
things that befell you in the past, let's say,
you may have to develop a relatively sophisticated
theory of the randomness of the world and come
to terms with that, but you may also have to
determine as precisely as you can what
insufficiencies you might have brought
to the situation that made you more
vulnerable than you needed to be.
So, for example, if you were bullied as a child,
maybe you still are concerned when you go to your
workplace, for example, especially if it's new,
that the same pattern might recur,
and you might remember with some apprehension
the misadventures you had when you were young.
And what that indicates is that, possibly,
that you haven't
redressed the insufficiencies in your personality
that led you to be the victim
of repeated bullying.
I used bullying as an example because one thing we
do know is that there is some
stability in the probability that a given child
will be a bully or be a victim of bullies.
And so I'm not trying to blame the victim
of a bully for the fact that that happens.
I'm just saying that if negative things have
befallen you in the past,
it's wisdom to determine what it is that you might
be doing wrong that's opening yourself up
to the possibility that those
sorts of things will happen to you.
And I would say,
if you're characterized by patterns of negative
events, then it's reasonably probable
that you're bringing something to the situation.
If it happens to you once, well, it's random.
And maybe if it happens to you twice, it's random.
But if it happens, if you have this same sort
of relationship with an intimate
partner three times, it's you.
Right, and that's an uncomfortable thing
to realize, and you can understand
why a stance like that might be criticized
in relationship to blaming the victim.
But look at it this way.
Even if it's 5% you,
maybe you should do something about it.
That's a useful thing to know, by the way,
if you're having
difficult discussions with an intimate partner
that you have now or a family member or a friend.
If you're in a situation where your interactions
aren't proceeding in the manner that you would
find optimal, one thing that's very much worth
doing is trying to figure out what
it is that you're doing wrong.
It's often very difficult, right?
Because if you're in a disagreement with someone,
the part of you that's seeking security is going
to want to insist that, look, we're having
a fight here, but it's at least 95% you.
And that's an easy—well,
and anger will make you think that.
Anger will also make you want to win.
The thing is, it might be 90% the other person,
although on average, it's probably not.
But even if it's 10% you,
that's something that is under your control
and you could rectify, and if you did,
might stop the 90% from making itself manifest
in the other person,
because you never know
to what degree your imperfections are
bringing about the conflicts in your life.
Now, you have to be careful to
meditate on that because you don't want to take
yourself apart, but you can learn techniques,
and we'll talk about them, too,
so that you don't force upon yourself
the necessity of a transformation
that's so rapid that it undermines you.
If it starts to become too threatening,
if the magnitude of change that you're
apprehending that's necessary for yourself is too
daunting, then you're biting off more than you can
chew and you should try to change slightly slower.
Maybe you should try to change
at the rate that you find optimal.
And that's a good thing to learn about yourself.
If you know that there's something that you have
to do and you're not doing it,
one tactic that you can employ that's
extremely useful is to shrink the task.
So maybe, I don't know,
maybe your garage is a mess and it's been that way
for 10 years and you can't get
yourself in there to clean.
It's like, well, maybe you should clean up
one corner in a week, something like that.
You can shrink the task until you'll find
a step forward that you will take.
And maybe if you're sophisticated,
you could find a step forward that you
would take, that you would take happily.
And this is a good thing to know, too, when you're
negotiating, say, with your wife or your husband.
You want them or you
or the two of you to make a change.
You can negotiate the change until you find
a change that's small enough and interesting
enough so you might both be willing
to experiment with it happily.
And there's a certain humility in that, right?
Because one of the things I noticed
as a clinician often was that,
if my clients were starting to make a positive
change in a new direction,
especially in a domain where they had had some
habitual weakness,
they often had to start that change at a level
that was so trivial that it
was embarrassing or shameful.
And so that's where the humility comes in.
There's going to be parts of your personality
that are pretty immature,
and the probability that you have to do something
shamefully small to start
improving that is extremely high.
But one thing to know about that is,
change accelerates.
And so even if you have to start slow,
that doesn't mean that that isn't going
to start a process that will accelerate.
And so even if your first steps have to be
embarrassingly tiny, that doesn't mean that you're
destined to only take embarrassingly tiny steps
during the entire process
of necessary transformation.
Carl Jung said, "The fool is
the precursor to the savior."
That's why comedians are
so necessary, by the way.
But what he meant by that was that,
if you want to make a change in a positive
direction, you have to allow
yourself to be a fool to begin with.
You're going to do things stupidly and badly when
you first do them, although maybe slightly
better than you had done them before.
And maybe even stupidly and badly
is better than pure avoidance.
And this is a good thing to know, too, when you're
negotiating again with your husband or your wife.
If there's something that you would want from them
that you think would help you
strengthen your commitment to the relationship,
you can negotiate with them
until you find a small change
that they're willing to do voluntarily,
and you can allow them to do that badly.
This is a very good thing to know,
especially if you're with someone
you're going to be with for a long time.
One of the things I used to do in my clinical
practice was some relationship counseling,
and one of the things
I would recommend to my clients
who were in a long-term relationship
or married was to go on dates with their partner.
And people were often very resistant
to that for all, probably because they tried it
a number of times and been burned in some way,
or they'd say things like, "Well, I don't have
to date because now I'm married."
It's like, OK,
you don't want any romance in your life?
And then they'd go out and have a date,
and they'd come back and tell me about
how wretched and miserable it went.
And then we do a little arithmetic,
which is always a useful thing to do
in a situation like this, let's say.
Maybe you want to have three intimate interactions
with your marital partner a week for 50 years.
Let's say that, or two.
Let's go with three.
That's 12 a month or about 150 a year.
And over 50 years, that's 7,500
interactions, 7,500.
OK, maybe you have to do
the first 200 of them badly.
And 200 is a lot,
but it's nothing compared to 7,500.
And so if you're willing to let yourself stumble
forward when you're improving things that repeat,
you allow yourself that space for play
and for error, then you can learn to incrementally
master in a manner that enables you
to become a master over the long run.
Another thing to think about that, too,
that it isn't so obvious when you first apprehend
it, is that your life in the main
is made up of things you repeat.
And we tend to downplay the significance of things
that we repeat because they're everyday, right?
They're normal, they're drab.
Coming home from work is a good example.
You're going to come home from work
five days a week.
There's going to be a transition
period from work that's 20 minutes.
And that transition period is going to happen
every day, and it's going to set
the tone for the rest of the day.
And so it's often the case that those transition
periods are awkward for people,
and they don't do anything about it.
And that's a huge mistake.
Because 20 minutes a day—
we can do the arithmetic—
that's 20 minutes a day times three.
So that's 2 hours a week, let's say.
It's 8 hours a month.
So it's 12 work days a year, essentially.
And so that's 5% of your life.
That's 5% of your life.
If you get 20 things like that right,
you have your whole life right.
And so you look at the things that repeat, right?
You master them.
You make incremental progress to making
them as perfect as they can possibly be.
You negotiate with your partner so
that that occurs,
and you allow that negotiation to
make itself manifest imperfectly
and in a manner that's ridden with errors
so that you can continually correct it.
And hopefully, after you repeat it
100 times, you get it right.
And you do that 20 times,
and everything in your life is set,
not only in order, but in the order
that's on the edge of play.
Right.
And you can do that.
You have to think about it, though.
You have to think about—
I see this with parents and their children.
You'll have someone with a two-year-old,
and every bedtime's a fight.
Well, you got to think that through, because
parents actually only spend about 20 minutes
a day in one-on-one interaction with their kids.
It's a much smaller fraction
of your time than you think.
And if that interaction is bedtime and every night
it's a misery, then what you've done is,
you've made that whole relationship into misery.
And you think, well,
it's only when I put my kid to bed.
It's like, no, it's not only that
because it happens every day.
And if that sets the pattern of your relationship,
that it's nothing but strife and foolish conflict,
then, well, how are you going to establish a good
relationship with your child and vice versa?
All they are is a problem to you.
And that's not a good thing.
And so, pay attention to the things that repeat.
They're very, very important.
That's your life.
People get obsessed about the exceptions,
vacations, the special occasions in their life.
And those are often a disappointment, by the way.
And that's fair enough because,
well, it's because people overvalue them,
and then they go have the experience
and it doesn't meet their expectations.
And so then they're miserable while they
have it and they have nothing but regret.
And part of the problem with that,
part of what's causing that,
is that they're paying way too much attention
to what's hypothetically exceptional and not
nearly enough attention
to what is normal and repeats.
And that's a form of pride, too,
because you might want to identify with only
the things in your life that are exceptional
and not the boring and drab day-to-day
things that you do all the time.
But you could elevate those
to the point of some optimized perfection.
You could tell you're doing that, by the way,
because you can do it in a state of play.
And that's also a very good thing to know.
It took me a long time to figure this out.
I spent decades trying to understand what
the opposite of tyrannical power was.
It's not an easy thing to conceptualize,
but I believe that it's play.
And I think that you know if you have
a situation mastered if you can do it playfully.
Imagine the situation where you're trying to put
your little kid to bed,
and that turns into a bout of play.
Well, then you've got it, and then you
do nothing but look forward to that.
And that would be a good deal.
If you were in a situation where you could do
nothing but look forward to the things you repeat
every day, that'd be a good
bargain to strike with yourself.
And it's also something to consider, too.
If you have things you're doing every day that you
dread, well, one question you might ask is,
is there something wrong with your attitude?
Because maybe there is,
and you should dig into that and find out.
But another conclusion you might draw is
maybe you're not doing the right thing.
And then you have to strategize carefully,
and that has to do with the development
of a vision, about maybe you hate your job.
And you think, well, I have to have this job
because I have to take care of my family.
That's a tyrannical attitude all the way through.
And you're blaming your family,
so that's a real good deal for them.
They're now the shackles that keep you
in slavery to a tyrannical job that you hate.
That's a lovely gift to lay
at the feet of your family.
There's a fair bit of pleasure
of martyrdom in that, too.
And you might say instead, and this is
what you can do, too,
if you're trying to understand the obstacles
that are getting in your way as you progress
is well, why are you stuck with this damn job?
And you got to think about that in detail.
I had clients, for example,
who were stuck in miserable jobs,
and I'd say to them, "Well,
let's take a look at your resume, your CV.
Bring it in next week."
And then they wouldn't.
Then I'd have to find out why.
It's like, well, why do you not
want to show your CV to someone?
Well, here's some reasons.
You haven't updated it for 10 years.
OK, so then, that's kind of daunting, right?
Because it's actually, like,
just because it's difficult,
you have to sit down and go through your life
and you have to structure
that in a way that's comprehensible.
But then, too, the problem with the CV is,
you have to reveal everything
about you that's embarrassing.
Maybe you have to paper over various aspects
of your stupidity with lies,
and that undermines your confidence about the CV
and about the job,
say, the job interview process,
because you have holes in your past
that you don't know what to do with.
Well, you face that.
You think, OK, well—you know, I had clients,
for example, they had 95% of their
undergraduate degree, and then they stopped.
And there's a reason for that.
I don't know.
Maybe they didn't want the responsibility that
would be attendant upon completing the degree.
Maybe it was a good way of getting back at their
father who forced them to go into engineering
when they wanted to be an artist.
There's some reason you stop with it 95% done.
And then you have to fix that because
otherwise you're embarrassed about it.
And if you're embarrassed about it,
then you're not going to be confident
when you go to your job interview.
And if you're afraid of not being confident,
you won't look for a job.
And then if you won't look for a job,
you'll blame your wife because
you have to be tyrannized at work.
That's a stupid game.
And so instead of that, you might figure out,
well, why the hell did you quit when you
were within grasping distance of the goal?
And god only knows why that is,
but maybe it's something that isn't even
true of you anymore.
Maybe you outgrew whatever stupidity
had made you do that 10 years ago.
To put your CV together,
you have to put your past together.
And maybe that takes two years.
If you want to find a job you actually like,
two years isn't too much of an investment to make.
And maybe you're terrified because you're going
to throw your CV out in the wind and
49 out of 50 times it's going to be rejected.
But then you could look at it actuarily
and presume, well, of course that's the case,
because lots of companies advertise positions
that don't even exist because they want to keep
a continual flow of CVs going through the system,
or they advertise because they're required
to legally and they already have a candidate,
or it could be that, at this particular moment,
you're not the best candidate for that particular—
there are a lot of reasons
why you're not going to get the job,
but they're true for virtually everyone.
And when you know that the base rate for CV
submission failure is 95%,
then you don't have to take it personally.
And you can think, "Well, I need a new job.
OK, I have to send out."
Well, you ask yourself, how many bloody
resumes can you stand to send out a week?
And that's a serious question, right?
How much disappointment can you take?
I don't know. Maybe you can handle 20
and maybe you can handle 5.
There's going to be some individual difference in
that, but you could consult yourself and find out.
And maybe you're so afraid to begin
with that you can only send out one.
It's like, one is a lot more than zero.
And once you've done one,
well, maybe you could do three.
And once you did three, maybe you could do 10.
And you could settle on, I'll send out—
you make a routine out of it.
I'll send out 10 resumes a week for, like, a year.
And if you do that, if you've updated your CV
and you're aiming at jobs that are hypothetically
within your purview, and you have a good story
to tell about why you would be the right
candidate, and you can figure that out, too.
If you have a good story to tell,
you're not going to be nervous about telling it.
So you got to ask yourself, well,
why should someone hire you?
And then you've got to discuss that with someone,
your wife or friends, and have them hammer away
at you until you know what you have to offer.
And then you can go in there with a bit
of confidence and you can say,
"Well, I don't know much.
I don't have any experience in this realm,
but here's a bunch of things that I've done.
And here's the investigations
that I've made about your company.
And this is why I think I'd be a good fit,
and this is what I can offer to you.
And I won't be a catastrophe," which is the one
thing everyone hiring really wants to know.
It's like, what do you think?
Can we do this together?
And if you have an attitude like that,
and you do get an interview,
which you will eventually, then the probability
that you'll get the job has gone up substantively.
And so you don't have to stay in your damn rut,
but you do have to figure out what elements
of what you don't understand, that chaos
and potential, are terrifying you into paralysis.
And then you think, "Well, I'm terrified
into paralysis by the magnitude
of the job search."
It's like, fair enough.
You may have lots of things
that you have to put right.
Make a list of all the things
that frighten you, right?
Maybe it's 15 things.
Then you can rank-order the list.
This frightens me the least.
Maybe I could try it.
And if all of the things frighten you too
much so you're paralyzed, break them down.
When I was counseling my clients to go on the job
search, one of their first assignments was often
"just open up your CV and look at it."
And this was an actual contract,
because when you're playing this game
with yourself, let's say, you can't cheat.
If you're terrified to go on the job search
and you've motivated yourself enough
so that you're willing to open your damn computer
and look through your CV, don't sit
down right then and start rewriting it.
It's a violation of the contract.
You're pushing yourself too hard.
What you should do instead is give yourself
a little pat in the back and say, "You know,
sad as it is, I was terrified to do this,
but I did it."
Right. So it's time to, like—
if you have a child and the child does
something new, you're not going to say to them,
if you have any sense,
"Why didn't you do twice as much?"
That's a great way to demoralize someone.
You also shouldn't do that to yourself.
If you've taken a step forward, like,
have a little recognition,
and maybe you've got someone around you,
if you're lucky, that you could tell what
you did to, and they would be happy about it.
And that's how you distinguish, by the way,
between the people you should have
around you and the people you shouldn't.
Because if you have people around you,
and you tell them that you made a small step
forward, and they make light of it or are cynical
about it or punish you for it,
you might think very hard about just who it
is that you're hanging around.
Because you want to be with people who note your
progress forward
and at least don't get in the way.
And that includes yourself, that's for sure.
All right.
So there may be some cleaning up
of the chaos in your past you have to do.
And you can note that.
Imagine you have a goal, getting a new job, and
you see that there are obstacles in your path
that are preventing you from moving forward.
And then you see that some of those
obstacles have to do with the past.
Well, so then
you have to clean up the past to the point where
those obstacles disappear, and then you
may find some obstacles in the present.
Maybe you don't think you're good at interviews.
Lots of people feel that way.
Well, then you have to practice that.
That's a present problem, let's say.
And although it may have its roots in the past,
maybe you're not sophisticated enough to conduct
yourself well in a job interview,
but that's something you can learn.
Write down 40 questions that you
think you might be asked.
Come up with an answer, not a lie, but an answer.
Here's the problem with lying.
Let's say you lie your way into a job.
Well, then you didn't get the job.
The lie got the job.
And if you had to lie to get the job,
probably it's not the job for you.
So then your reward is that you get a job
that isn't for you and that you don't deserve.
Well, that's a hell of a way to start a job.
Why don't you start a job that is for you,
that you do deserve, that you could do.
That'd be a lot better plan.
And you might say, well, I have to get
a pretty dismal job given my qualifications.
It's like, you start where you are
or you start on a falsehood.
And one of the things,
there's this phenomenon in economics
called the Matthew principle, by the way.
And the Matthew principle is,
"To those who have everything, more will be given.
And from those who have nothing,
everything will be taken."
And this is a reflection of a phenomenon called
the Pareto distribution.
And the Pareto distribution works like this:
progress is not linear.
It's geometric or exponential.
Once you start accruing money, the probability
that you'll accrue more starts to increase.
This is why a very small percentage
of the people have all the money.
If you have a million, it's hard to make—
if you have no money, it's hard to make a dollar.
If you have a million, it's a lot easier to make
the next million than it is
to make the first million.
And that continues.
If you have 400 million, it's a lot
easier to make a billion, et cetera.
This is true, by the way,
for every domain of accomplishment.
Once you've recorded one album,
it's much easier to record the next
than it was to record the first.
And the third is even easier than the second.
Success builds upon itself.
And so what that means,
and this is a good thing to know,
as I said before, even if you have to start slow,
that doesn't mean you're doomed to slow.
And even if you have to take
a job that's beneath you—
which is not a good way of conceptualizing it,
by the way; if it's actually matched to your
talents, you should be grateful for it—
if you do a stellar job at that job,
the probability that someone will notice
and push you along is extremely high.
This is something also that people who are
bitter and hold back don't understand.
I used to get undergraduates come to work with me
in my lab, and I had a lot fewer positions than
there were inquiring undergraduates, right?
So they were high-demand positions.
And generally, what I would do was give
the undergraduate who's asking a task,
a real one, because I'd have some—maybe I needed
them to go investigate some psychological
phenomenon, make me a little report about it,
a research review, and I'd give them that
obligation or opportunity.
Well, if you are talking with someone who has
resources that you might want access to,
if they ask you to do something,
that's not an obligation.
That's an opportunity.
And if you have the two things
confused, you're doomed.
If you regard the things that will
move you forward as an obligation,
how in the world are you going to move forward?
So what would happen inevitably
is that some of the undergraduates would go
and do just a stellar job,
and it would be done in two days.
And then others would come back to me a week later
and say, "Well, all these things
came up and I couldn't do it."
And often the story was very plausible,
because they had family trouble.
I don't know what the hell the problem was.
It was some real problem, or maybe not,
but at least it sounded like a real problem.
But then I'd go ask the people who did it,
who actually did the job,
and they had just as many problems.
They just didn't let the problem
stop them from doing the job.
And so then I would hire the undergraduates
who actually did the job and not hire
the undergraduates who didn't do the job.
And you might say, "Well, that's pretty
mean because those poor people had problems."
It's like, well, maybe they had problems,
and maybe they were a problem.
And one of the things I noticed was that if I
pulled people into my lab who were
a problem, that was a problem.
And it wasn't just a problem
that I had to deal with.
It was a problem that often infected the entire
lab and especially demoralized
the people who were doing a good job.
Right. And so,
well, if you have to start where you are
and you're grateful for the opportunity and you
make the proper sacrifices and you work,
then anyone with any sense will notice that.
And anyone you want to work for has enough
sense to notice when you're doing a good job.
Now, if you're in a job where you're doing a good
job and no one is noticing,
you should ask yourself two questions.
Do the people that you're working
for know that you're doing a good job?
Because it's possible that you're doing things so
efficiently that you're invisible and you're not
very good at self-promotion,
which is actually just communication.
If you're doing a good job for people,
they need to know it.
And one of the times that you can
inform them about that is when you
go ask for a raise or a promotion.
You need a little list.
"Here's a bunch of things I did that made your
life a hell of a lot easier than it might have
otherwise been, and perhaps more profitable,"
that you may not have even known about.
"And if you produce an increment of salary of this
magnitude or give me a bit more flexibility or
a promotion or some other opportunity,
here's a bunch of things I could do for you
that would make your life even better."
It's like, if you have that story and it's real,
and you present that to your employer,
and they don't go,
"That sounds like a pretty damn good deal.
Are you sure that that raise is enough?",
then maybe you should decide whether or not
that's not the right place for you to be working.
And before you do that, too,
you might have already wanted to get your CV
in order and to have started sending it out to see
what sort of market demand there is for your
skills, so you can tell your employer as well
that you have other offers that are pending.
And then you put yourself in a pretty
damn good bargaining position.
Part of the reason, by the way,
that women do not make as much money as men—
it's one of many reasons—
is that they're not as good as men
at promoting their own accomplishments.
It's part of being agreeable
and higher in negative emotion.
I saw this when I worked in civil service in
Alberta, years ago, when I was a kid, 20 years old.
I saw that the bureaucracy was basically run
by 50-year-old women who did all the work,
and all of that credit was taken by narcissists
who pretended that it was them and took all
the credit from the conscientious
older women who were working.
Right, an ugly situation.
And you could lay that at the feet
of the narcissists for being
manipulative and psychopathic.
But those women should have learned that doing
a great job invisibly is not a very good strategy.
People need to know.
And that means you shouldn't be tooting your own
horn constantly because that's just annoying.
But it does mean that the people for whom you're
doing a good job should know you're doing it.
And you should also note how much
reward you need for doing a good job.
Because if you're doing a great job and no one
ever notices, maybe you're conscientious enough so
that that'll be sufficiently motivating for you.
But most of us would like to be rewarded
for a job well done on some schedule.
That's something else you can negotiate
with your wife, your husband, your kids.
It's like,
one of you in a marriage is going to cook.
Well, a little appreciation for that now and then
tends to improve the quality of the meals,
and the atmosphere around the table.
One of the things you have to
discover about yourself,
and this is also part of developing a vision is,
well, what's the reward schedule
that's necessary for you?
And none, that's not a good reward schedule.
And it's something to discover, right?
Maybe someone only has to say something
positive to you once every month.
Who knows?
Or maybe it's twice a day.
There's going to be some temperamental
variability that characterizes you in that regard.
You're probably going to need to be rewarded
more for things that you're just trying as well.
But this is a good thing to meditate on.
How much notice do you need when
you're doing something good?
And this is something
to negotiate with your partner.
When you do something for them,
you can teach them to notice it, and you can
also let them know what they need to say.
This is something else that's useful to know.
Say you're having a dispute with your wife,
and she wanted you to say
something other than what you said.
Now, that's what she's going
to let you know, first of all.
"I would like you to say something
other than what you just said."
"What do you want me to say?"
Well, then she's going to say,
"Well, if you loved me, you'd know."
Everyone laughs when I make that joke.
Yeah, well, it's too vague.
It's like, "No, I want to know exactly
what you would want me to say.
If I could say to you what would make
you happiest, what would that be?"
Now you're in trouble because
you have to figure that out.
Then you have to reveal that.
Then you're going to be annoyed because you're
going to say, "Well, that's not genuine."
It's like, yeah,
maybe it won't be the first 20 times.
But maybe the person can get good at it,
and by the 50th compliment,
not only will have the words right,
but they'll also have the sentiment right.
You have to let people be stupid about how
they're treating you well to begin with.
The other thing you can notice, too,
is that if your partner does do something
that you really appreciated,
something small and subtle, let's say,
they sneak something good in just to see what
might happen, if you're smart enough to jump
on that, and you have to not be too resentful
about their existence to do this,
if you're smart enough to jump on that and say,
"Ha, I saw what you did.
This is how you greeted me when I came home.
I got a hug, for example, instead of an immediate
litany of never-ending complaints.
That was a very lovely way to reenter the house."
If you're very, very—this is something that's
very useful with employees, too, and coworkers.
If you see someone doing a good job and you say,
"Hey, here's what you did,"
and you say it in detail,
"I saw that and it was good," man,
you do that a hundred times if you're
running a restaurant,
you do that to your employees,
any of the employees worth keeping,
they'll be working themselves to the bone
to get another reward like that.
People really like that.
The Skinner, the Skinner behavioral psychologist,
could train animals to do anything.
He trained pigeons to guide guided missiles
over enemy territory by pecking on photographs.
That's hard.
Skinner noticed that reward was the most effective
form of behavioral transformation,
but it was subtle, because to reward an animal
for doing something you want it to do,
you have to wait around until it does the thing,
and then you have to reward them.
And so this is the same in your household.
If you're watching your kids, maybe your kid
by accident cleaned something up one day.
You can notice that.
You say, look, maybe they're five.
"That was the sort of thing
an eight-year-old would do.
Good work, kid.
Here's what you did."
They'll smile like mad.
And the probability that they'll do something
like that again radically magnifies.
And kids are very good at generalizing, too.
So not only will they do that thing again,
but they'll do things in that category again.
And that's a fun way of interacting with people
in your family, because targeted reward
is a pleasure to give and also to receive.
And so it's a great way of establishing harmony
in your household without the scraps,
the fights that might otherwise be necessary.
Sometimes you have to settle something,
and that requires dredging up all sorts of things
that everyone perhaps would rather leave buried,
and attempting to sort through them.
That's quite demanding.
But targeted reward requires attention,
but it's extremely effective and it's
a very pleasant thing to engage in.
All right, so there may be things in your
present that you have to sort out.
Maybe you have to find your
damn CV on your computer.
Even that can be a nightmare.
One of the things I saw with my particularly
disorganized clients was that I'd ask them to get
their CV off their computer,
and then maybe they'd bring their laptop in,
and the whole bloody thing
was just a catastrophic mess.
There were files everywhere.
The computer hard drive was
a reflection of their psyche.
Everything was everywhere,
and all that was valuable was lost.
And so maybe one of the things that,
the first thing you have to encounter when you try
to open your CV is the fact that your computer is
such a bloody mess that you can't find anything.
Imagine that, just imagine that.
So someone's in a job they hate.
And in order to fix that,
they have to sort out their CV.
And to do that, they have to find it.
And to do that, they have to confront their
computer, which isn't that big a dragon.
It's not nothing, but it's not cancer.
It's trouble.
But then that's annoying and embarrassing.
And so instead of doing that, they don't do it.
And then they have the job they hate for 30 years.
Right. Yeah.
Not smart.
And you could also see that there's a certain
humility involved in noticing that your failure
to confront the mess on your
computer might end your life.
Right.