All right.
Well, how else do we put up walls?
We organize ourselves politically, right?
And so we have hierarchies of social
organization that surround us.
And we've figured out how to formalize that so we
can have conflicts and compete and cooperate
without degenerating into absolute chaos.
And then we also frame the world with our bodies.
So part of the way that we solve the problem
of the fact that we're surrounded by an infinite
amount of that which we do not understand
is that we can't see that much.
You hear what you hear, but not everything.
And you see what you see,
but by no means everything.
What you focus on visually is a very, very tiny
percentage of what you could conceivably see.
You don't see what's behind you.
You don't see what's to the side of you.
If I'm looking at you,
I'm not looking at you, right?
So even that focal perception restricts.
Our bodies are—what did Huxley say?
Who's the philosopher?
I can't remember his name at the moment.
Huxley wrote about this in The Doors
of Perception, is that there's a world of infinite
wonder around us all the time,
but that infinite wonder is also overwhelming.
And one of the things that being embodied does is
restrict our view to the point where it's
narrow enough so that we can master it.
You don't see more than you can understand,
perhaps.
It restricts it.
And so embodiment is another invisible frame.
It excludes as much as it includes;
it actually excludes more.
And then
there are sub-bodies, so to speak, within us.
And you could think about those as instincts.
Your senses frame the world.
So you see the world visually, you hear the world,
you touch the world, you taste
the world, you smell the world.
Those are avenues of encountering what you
don't understand, so you can sample them.
Your motivations and your emotions provide you
with the basic structures of understanding
that help you categorize the world.
And they're there to begin with.
So for example, if you say to your wife,
"I'm hungry," she doesn't say,
"What do you mean, hungry?"
And the reason she doesn't say
that is because she gets hungry, too.
And so you can take that for granted.
And the reason she gets hungry is because you
have a biological system that operates within you.
It's a subset of your body that regulates food
intake and lets you know by craving
when it is that you need to eat.
And that's a universal experience.
And it's one way that we parse
the world apart instinctively.
And so if you're hungry,
your goal is to find something to eat.
And so what happens when you're hungry,
it isn't a drive that propels you
deterministically through the world.
What happens when you're hungry is that your
hunger takes a grip of your vision,
your internal vision.
It says, "Your goal is now
to find something to eat."
And so now you're set up in a perceptual frame
that orients the world in its entirety around the
task that you're undertaking,
which is to find food.
And so the best way to think about
hunger is as a personality or as a story.
Hunger is the personality or the story that drives
you into the realm of conceptualization
that has food at its end.
In the Exodus story, the Promised Land
is the land of milk and honey.
And that's partly because archaic people were
hungry a lot, and milk is fat and honey is sugar.
And when you don't have enough to eat,
ice cream, that's sugar and fat, that's paradise.
Right.
And so when you're hungry, food is paradise.
And so, and it sets up—it's not a drive.
It's not a deterministic drive,
because if you're hungry,
you might have to solve extremely complex
problems, like how to share food with other
people, for example, in order to eat.
So the hunger is a sophisticated subpersonality.
And we have a variety of intrinsic,
instinctual subpersonalities that we
define as motivations that we all share.
That's part of what makes us
mutually comprehensible and fundamentally human.
And so various physiologists have broken these
motivational states down in various ways.
But one reasonable rubric
based on biological analysis is that you
have two broad classes of motivation.
One is designed to make sure
that you continue to exist.
Those are self-preservation motivations or
self-maintenance, and the others are reproductive.
And so, there's you, and you have to keep yourself
going, but there's you in the social world, right?
So you need a mate, and you
to get along with other people.
And there are different classes of motivation
that serve those different needs.
So in terms of self-maintenance,
you get hot or you get cold.
If you're taking care of an infant,
you see this very clearly,
because if your infant is distressed,
it's usually because there's some basic
motivational need that's not addressed.
They're hot, they're cold, they're wet,
they're thirsty, they're hungry,
they're tired, right?
Or they need to use the washroom.
It's something like that.
And so if you're taking care of an infant, you
run through these different—is the baby too hot?
Is the baby too cold?
Does the baby need something to eat?
Is the baby tired?
And those are your basic initial solutions,
and they suffice 95% of the time.
And that's a good thing to know,
if you have an infant.
It's like, you go through the checklist.
Even with little kids, it's the same thing.
If they start to misbehave,
they're often hungry—adults for that matter, too.
I noticed when we had little kids that we'd take
them out to a social event,
and after like an hour, they'd start to misbehave,
and then we'd leave, and my wife
and I would think, "It was time to go."
And the kids figured that out before we did.
It's like, the adults will get crabby
15 minutes after the kids get crabby.
So anyways, you have these basic in-built
motivations, and they're there at the beginning.
And a two-year-old, for example, is really
nothing but a bundle of those motivations.
And one of the things that makes
kids delightful is they just bounce through those
motivational states, and they sort of appear.
If a kid's angry,
some kids in particular, they'll have a tantrum.
It's like, they're just 100% rage.
I've seen 30-year-olds have tantrums.
I tell you, man, you want to call
the police when that happens.
It's really terrifying because a two-year-old
who's having a tantrum is
completely out of control.
But they're, like, two.
So what are they going to do?
They're only this tall and you can just push
them over if they cause too much trouble.
But if you're 30 and you have a tantrum,
oh my god, it's quite the terrifying display.
And so, a two-year-old will cry and be enraged
and be hungry and then be so happy
that you can hardly even stand it.
Neither can they.
And they just cycle through
these motivational states.
And there's a real purity in that and a real
intensity that makes being around them fun.
But they can't take care of themselves,
and they're nothing but a handful of problems.
And if you have someone who's adult
who's like that, like, god help you.
So it's just fine when you're two,
but when you're 30, it's getting a little old.
One of the things that happens as a child matures,
they have these in-built instinctive systems,
and you might say, well, maybe that's good enough.
And it's not, because the systems really
present problems,
but they're not that good at offering solutions.
So when you're hungry,
that's not the same as eating.
It's the problem.
The eating is the solution.
The hunger is the problem.
When you're thirsty, it's the same thing.
These in-built motivational systems
don't tell you how to solve the problem.
And sometimes the problem is
that the motivations conflict.
You see this sometimes.
Like, are you too hungry
to sleep or too tired to eat?
And you can see that you can have
motivational problems of your own.
Maybe you hate someone, but you're
terribly sexually attracted to them.
So that's another place where
motivational systems will conflict.
And so what happens as you mature is that those
motivational systems have to be integrated so
that they can be
satisfied over a long period of time,
so they can be satisfied in relationship to each
other, and so they can be satisfied
in the presence of other people.
So maybe, you can see that with kids.
So what are the elementary forms of socialization?
Toilet training, because now there are lots of
kids who are in grade 1 who aren't toilet-trained.
That's become a real problem in places like
the UK, is that we've allowed our families to get
so fragmented that there are six-year-old
kids who haven't been toilet-trained.
Stunning.
And you can see that if you haven't got that
figured out by the time you're four,
and that's really pushing it,
that's going to cause a lot of social problems,
to say the least.
You're just not getting anywhere in life
if you haven't got that under control.
And so you see that that's a place where
a basic biological motivation has to be integrated
into a pattern of behavior that's socially
acceptable,
so that other things that are socially acceptable,
other solutions that are socially
acceptable, can be implemented.
And that's what you're trying to do
with your children.
This is a good thing to know because
the Freudian model,
which is interesting but wrong, is
the human being—well, it is,
but interestingly wrong is useful, right?
And it is interestingly wrong.
So Freud conceptualized us in part as an id,
which was a, what would you call, gathering place
of instincts, mostly sexual for Freud,
but instinct, instinctual compulsion and drive.
And that would meet the superego,
which was basically the social, patriarchal social
community, potentially internalized, that says no.
It's inhibition.
It's like a Rousseauian model, in some sense,
with a bit more negativity added.
You're a mass of impulses.
The impulses have to be met with control.
OK, but that brings us to the force problem.
It's like, is it control that you're
trying to institute on your children?
The problem with that is,
if you use force and control,
they're going to rebel,
or you're going to intimidate them, or you're
going to, or you're going to, what would you call?
You're going to make them into resentful followers
of stupid rules they don't understand,
which is also not a good outcome.
You can do that to yourself, too,
by forcing yourself to do things that
you're actually not inclined to do.
It's complicated because you
want to discipline yourself.
So what are you doing?
Well, you're offering the child a better game.
As I said before, my son, when he was little,
he was a pretty aggressive little kid.
He had a good temper, and
I liked playing with him.
But now and then he'd get out of hand and get
stubborn, and I'd go have him sit on the steps.
And it was so interesting watching him,
because, maybe,
it probably happened from the time he was about 12
months till he was about two, something like that.
He'd sit on the steps because he, I don't know,
he was enraged about something
that didn't go his way.
And the rule was, sit on the steps until you
can play again, until you can act like a civilized
human being that other people
would like to have around.
And so as soon as he would do that,
he could get off the steps.
It was so interesting watching him do that,
because he'd sit on the steps
with his fists clenched, his teeth clenched,
and I'd go tap and say, "Are
you ready to get off the steps?"
"Not yet."
But you could see, so what was happening is,
he was trying to integrate those powerful forces
of rage into a personality that would
enable him to maintain his social relations.
Now, look.
If you can imagine this as an adult,
is maybe you're having a difficult conversation
with your wife,
and she's afraid to do that because you have
a temper,
which means that you're not well socialized.
She'll say something provocative,
maybe that's just related to an actual problem,
or maybe she's given you a poke just to find out
what kind of son of a bitch you are,
and you can't control your anger.
And so what does that mean?
It means that you haven't mastered the capacity
to integrate the full range of your aggression
into a sophisticated personality.
That makes you dangerous.
Part of the reason you see that in a developing
relationship, for example, between a man and a
woman, both partners will test each other out.
And women will say provocative things to men.
And men think, "Why the hell is that going on?"
And the answer is something like,
well, the women want to find out,
if you're annoyed, if you turn into a murderous
tyrant, because if you do, you're probably
not the best person to have around children.
And that's a really crucial thing to discover.
And so you don't discover
that just by asking someone.
You have to poke them a bunch and see.
It's like, can I elicit
something in you that's untoward?
And that's a deadly game.
And it's not even necessary that the people
who are playing it even know they are,
but people will definitely play games like that,
and they need to because you need to know.
And it isn't that you control your temper.
There are times when you have to,
but that's not right.
My son,
who learned to integrate the part of him that was
aggressive, became a very good athlete,
and he's very competitive. He really likes to win,
and his mother is like that as well.
But he learned how to—that meant the aggression is
still there, but it's replicated at a higher level
of development that integrates it
with all sorts of other things.
If you want to be aggressive while you're playing
a sport, you have to play it in a way
that other people want to play with.
Then you get to have your aggression,
but in these walled boundaries.
And partly what you're trying to do with your
children is to teach them
the sophisticated games that enable all of their
needs and wants to be
met over the longest possible span of time
in the broadest possible set of situations.
And that's not inhibition.
It's not superego against id.
It's the integration of those lower-order
personalities into a higher-order
personality that does meet all the demands.
And so maybe by the time you're 13 or 14, 15,
you're sophisticated enough as a male so that you
can do a good job playing competitively
on a sports team, and you're a good team player,
and you give credit where credit is due,
and you don't take all the glory when you win,
and people like you, and you're a winner,
and that makes you attractive.
And so now your self-maintenance goals
and the integration of your personality has also
made you sexually and socially attractive, right?
And so then you're playing a very complex
and sophisticated game that meets all
of the requirements of those subordinate systems
simultaneously, and even more importantly,
does that in a way that enables other people to do
it at the same time, and maybe even better
than they could if you weren't around.
Right, and so, when you think your personality,
you might think your personality has a goal.
That's an interesting way of thinking about it.
You can see what your goal is,
the intrinsic goal of your personality,
by asking yourself to imagine
what it is that you might want.
This is a very good exercise.
We'll talk about this tomorrow,
practically speaking.
But you could imagine, daydream, you know.
If your life could be set up the way that you
wanted it to, we're assuming you
bring a bit of wisdom to bear on this.
Well, what would that look like?
Probably you'd want to have a partner,
and maybe you'd want her to like
you, and maybe you'd like to have a family,
and the same thing would apply there.
You could get along with your parents.
You could get along with your siblings.
You love your children,
and they would respect you.
You'd have some friends.
Well, if you could have the friends you wanted,
what would that look like?
And what would your friendships be like?
You could do that with your career,
and you can do that with your education.
We'll step through this tomorrow when we
talk about these things more concretely.
But those are all those visions
of what you want and need,
if you're asking yourself honestly,
are the collective voice
of your integrated instincts that are attempting
to lay out a description of who you could be if
you could satisfy everything that needs
to be satisfied at the same time.
Now, you imagine it's three in the morning
and you've done something stupid
and your conscience comes to visit;
and it's bothering you because
you are a fool and you know it.
You might say, well, what
the hell is that voice of conscience?
Is it you?
And if it's you, why can't you just shut it off?
And if it's you, why is it calling you to task?
Why can't you just tell your conscience,
"Reorient yourself there, buddy.
I can do whatever the hell I want.
I don't want to feel guilty about it afterwards.
I don't want to feel disgusted
or ashamed or that I'm lesser.
Why would I bother with that?"
And if your conscience is you,
in some simple sense, why doesn't it just listen,
which it doesn't?
And the answer is something like,
the person you could be,
if you were all the things you could be,
is calling you to task for your shortcomings
in relationship to that domain of possibility.
And you could think about that as—one way
of thinking about that is
that that's your higher self.
Carl Jung made a distinction between
the persona and the ego and the self.
So the persona is what you show
of yourself to other people.
Now, that can be a falsehood,
in which case you're manipulative,
or it can be the sort of thing that you do when
you go to visit the teller at a bank,
because the teller says, "How are you?"
And they don't really care.
And you say, "I'm fine," even though you're not.
And the reason you do that isn't
because you're both lying.
It's because the teller wants to see,
"Are you sane enough
to play the simplest of social games so that I can
be reasonably certain that when I do my small
task with you, all hell won't break loose?"
And so they say, "How are you?"
And if you say, "I'm fine," they think, "Well,
you got the basics down.
It's probably safe to proceed."
Well, that's what small talk is for.
And you need to have a persona because lots
of time when you're interacting with other people,
they don't want to know who you are.
You don't want to know everything
about the person who's selling clothes.
When you're on a bus and someone sits down beside
you and starts telling you their life story,
you know that's not good.
You know that's not good, put it that way.
So that's the persona.
And you want to have a well-manicured persona
just so you're not a pain in the neck.
You don't want to confuse yourself with that.
You're not your social role.
Then you have the ego behind that.
And the ego is more like who you think you are.
And that's a partial thing, too,
because what the hell do you know about yourself?
You probably don't know much about yourself, more
about yourself than you know about anybody else.
You're very, very, very complicated.
You just think about the internal machinery.
All the subsystems that make up you, and then that
going all the way down to the subatomic level.
Man, your brain is more complicated than
anything else that exists, except other brains.
You're one complicated thing.
There are more connections,
patterns of connections in your brain than there
are subatomic particles in the visible universe.
So that's how complicated you are.
And that's why your wife or your husband
can hardly stand living with you.
And so the thing that holds you responsible,
your conscience, let's say,
that's what you could become.
That's the unity that you could become
attempting to make itself manifest in the moment.
It does that all sorts of interesting ways.
This is such a cool thing to know.
It does that by calling you on your misbehavior.
Now, your conscience can malfunction,
because you can be socialized in a way that makes
you too harsh on yourself,
or maybe you've lied to yourself a bunch,
and so you've warped your relationship
with your internal guidance system.
It's another reason you shouldn't lie,
because you program yourself erroneously,
and then you will report falsely to yourself.
And then one day you'll be in real trouble,
and you'll need to know what's true,
and you won't be able to tell,
and then you'll be in real trouble.
So one of the reasons you don't lie is because you
want to keep your vision clear,
because you're going to need it at some point.
OK, so imagine that your conscience will call
you out on deviations from the proper course.
OK, and I already defined the proper course.
The proper course
solves the problems you need to solve
over the medium to long run
and in relationship to all the other problems,
for you, in a way that's
maximally socially acceptable.
It's a very complicated dynamic.
It's something
like being an athlete on multiple teams.
Maybe it's something like being an athlete
on multiple teams and performing well in school.
You could see that there's a pattern there.
You'd be a good athlete and good student,
and the pattern would be good.
Good.
Good athlete, good student,
and then that would decompose into the various
sports team memberships and the various academic
disciplines that you're excelling in.
It's a hierarchy.
Well, that hierarchy
of attainment is your identity.
And insofar as you've been true to yourself, then
that's going to be successful and differentiated.
OK, so your conscience will call
you on deviations from that path.
So that's a good thing to know.
That's like the voice of the higher self within.
That's a religious phenomenon,
one of the things you see happening in the Old
Testament, for example, with the Prophet Elijah.
Elijah is the first person in the Judeo-Christian
pantheon who identifies
the voice of God with conscience.
So he's a prophet that stands
up against the nature god.
So before that, one of the presuppositions of
the archaic pagans was that the divine was
embedded in the natural world,
the force of nature.
And you can imagine that.
You go look at the Grand Canyon; it
inspires you with awe.
And you look at the stars and the ocean;
you experience a hurricane.
You could see that you could
place divinity in the natural world.
Elijah was the first person,
at least in this pantheon of stories, who
made a psychological interpretation,
said the thing that should orient you
most properly is the still,
small voice within, the voice of conscience.
And so that's a very interesting
thing to know, right?
And you think, well, what's that a reflection of?
Well, it's not you, as we said,
because if it was you, you could control it.
It's got an autonomy, your conscience.
It speaks to you.
It'll hold you accountable.
Well, you have to ask yourself,
well, what is it that's holding you accountable?
And you could say, well,
it's the voice of society within.
It's like, well,
that's not really much of an answer, actually,
because then you have to ask, well,
where did the voice of society come from?
What's the derivation of that spirit?
Because then that would be tradition extending
over thousands and thousands
or tens of thousands of years.
It doesn't really dissolve the mystery.
If it's the voice of society within, it's
the voice of the proper social orientation within.
So then it's the spirit
of proper social orientation.
You still end up with the same problem.
It's an autonomous spirit of some sort.
And so it's the thing that will
call on your misbehavior.
There's another element to it,
too, that's worth knowing about.
So I'll tell you another story.
So this is from Exodus, again.
So Moses is going about his business
in Exodus as a shepherd.
And that was actually a pretty admirable
occupation in archaic times because
sheep are hard to take care of and there's lambs,
they're hard to take care of and
they're delicious.
And so there's lions and wolves around
the Middle East at that time and plenty of them.
And so if you were a shepherd,
you had to take care of yourself and you
had to protect the lambs from lions.
And that was hard.
So you were like a major league
character if you could manage that.
It was a relatively low-status job,
but that didn't mean it wasn't difficult.
You could see that it would be an analogy
for protecting the vulnerable
from the worst of all possible predators.
That's why the shepherd, for example,
is an analog to the savior, for example,
in the Judeo-Christian pantheon.
Anyways, Moses has left Egypt temporarily.
He killed some Egyptian who was torturing a
Hebrew slave, and he had to make tracks.
And so he went to this foreign country,
and he got himself a couple of wives.
And he had a father-in-law he got along with,
and he established a life there.
And so he's wondering around being a shepherd,
feeling pretty good about himself.
And something beckons to him.
Something captures his attention off to the side.
It's a burning bush.
Now, it's not like an oak tree on fire
right in the middle of his path.
It's something that you could pass by.
Now, a burning bush, what does that mean?
Well, a bush is a little tree,
and a tree is commonly a symbol of life,
partly because life branches,
partly because a tree is alive, partly because
we lived in trees for 20 million years.
We have a very integral relationship with trees.
That's why we think of
old growth forests as sacred.
We have a very tight relationship with trees.
A tree is a symbol of life,
a symbol of being, let's say, of living being.
And fire is a symbol of transformation.
And so, a burning bush is something
living so intensely that it's in flame.
It's a compelling—you know how compelling fire is.
You can't take your eyes off fire.
And so this is something compelling that
calls to Moses, and he deviates from his path,
and he goes to investigate.
OK, so when does that happen in your life?
It happens when you get interested in something.
And you see, that has an autonomy, too.
Maybe you're 15 and you're in class and a new girl
comes in and it's like, man,
you're instantly interested in her.
It's like, well,
where the hell did that come from?
It's not you.
Not exactly.
Maybe you're not even happy about it.
I mean, that happens in all
sorts of doomed relationships.
You get interested in someone, and it's hopeless
and pointless or miserable and painful,
but you can't shake it.
And your interest is a strange
thing because it comes upon you.
It makes itself manifest.
It's not something that you create.
You can squelch it.
You can fail to follow it.
But it's very difficult
to elicit it if it's not there.
I had a client, for example, who, he
was with a woman that he really—she
was a good friend of his, but there was no
sexual chemistry as far as he was concerned.
And he really liked her,
and he had gone out with a number of women
who he had plenty of sexual chemistry
with and just horrible relationships with.
So he was happy that he was with someone that he
liked, but he couldn't get that spark going.
And no matter how hard he tried,
that didn't happen.
And the reason I'm telling you that is because
you see that interest has a certain autonomy.
It's something that calls to you.
It's an old idea that people
have a calling or a destiny.
And one of the things I've done in my podcast,
I get to talk to people who've
had various levels of accomplishment.
I'm always interested in how they got interested
in what they got interested in,
because something gripped them
with enough force that they followed and
became disciplined, and then
that turned into success, right?
OK, so you find something that's interesting to
you, it calls to you, and then you can establish,
what, a relationship with it?
Is that the right way of thinking about it?
Likely.
So what happens to Moses is
that he starts investigating this.
He gets closer and closer to it.
Imagine you're interested in something;
now you start to investigate it.
So now you're getting closer to it.
And as you get closer to it, it deepens.
You know that if you have an intellectual,
artistic interest.
The more you study it, the deeper it gets.
It starts to spread out,
so it covers more and more territory,
and it gets deeper, whatever that means.
What does deeper mean?
It means you get closer to the basics,
you get closer to the foundation.
You get closer to the assumptions.
If you start to get to know someone deeply,
you understand their deepest motivations,
the pattern of their motivation
all the way down to the root.
You go down the levels to go deeper.
Well, that's what happens when Moses
starts to approach this burning bush.
He realizes he's starting
to tread on sacred ground.
So he takes off his shoes,
and then he continues his investigation.
That's a gesture of humility,
to take off your shoes in that context.
OK, so now you're pursuing something that's
interesting to you,
and you allow that to change you as you pursue it.
And you do that in humility,
assuming that if you pursue this interest
honestly, that it will lead you,
it'll lead you to a better place.
That's a good way of thinking about it.
It'll change you.
Maybe it'll burn things away
from you that shouldn't be there.
That's another thing.
That happens, for example,
if you are attracted to someone,
you may do backflips to sort yourself out
so that you're more attractive to them.
Because if you're compelled by something and you
want to be worthy of it, you'll let go
of the things that aren't worthy in you.
Let them burn away.
So that's part of the symbolism
of the burning bush.
Anyways, he keeps investigating,
and then the voice of God itself speaks to him
and reveals itself as the ground of being.
So what happens is, Moses
establishes a relationship with this thing
that compels him, that's so deep that he now
understands right what's at the bottom of things.
And that's when he becomes a leader.
God tells him,
"Now you can go and face the Pharaoh,"
which is not a trivial thing, because
he's an absolute monarch of the biggest
empire that ever existed up to that time.
"And you can tell him that he's misbehaving
and that he has to let his workers be free."
Well, that's a major daunting mission.
But the implication of the story is that if you
pursue those things that compel your interest with
sufficient depth, you'll get to the depths,
and that will transform you into a
leader, right now.
So then you think there's a dynamic there.
Very interesting dynamic.
On the one hand, you can pursue what
you're interested in, what calls to you.
You have to decide what that is,
and you have to seek it out.
And on the other hand, you can attend
to the dictates of your conscience.
Both of those are autonomous to some degree.
They're outside of you,
or deep inside of you, or both.
And if you let that dynamism play out,
that'll transform you across time.
And you might say, well,
transformation has no direction.
That's what you say if you're nihilistic,
let's say.
But we already defined a direction,
which is that if you develop, if you're primitive,
you're hungry and you cry,
that's your whole strategy.
And someone offers you food, and that works if
you're two because someone takes care of you.
But it's not much of a long-term strategy.
As you mature, you have to determine how you can
take care of yourself.
And you get better and better at doing
that in more and more situations.
And you get better at doing that in a way
that makes you socially desirable.
And there's no upper limit to that.
And so if you were everything you could be,
you'd be welcome and useful wherever you went.
And if you're not that,
you will call yourself out on that.
You'll go to a party and you'll be embarrassed.
You'll be embarrassed that you're not as socially
fluent as the ideal that beckons within you.
And that can be a devastating realization.
There's no ideal without judgment.
But by the same token,
that's the possibilities that reside within
you making themselves manifest to you.
They do that by capturing your interest.
So that's such a cool thing to understand is that
this assumes, again, that you've established
the proper relationship with yourself.
This is why you shouldn't lie.
If you don't lie, the things that will make
you develop optimally will call to you.
If you lie, you'll pervert that vision,
and then you'll follow false idols.
And that's not a good idea, because these
are very fundamental orienting mechanisms.
And if you interfere with their function
by falsifying them, they'll lead you astray
in ways that you won't even be conscious of.
And you can tell if that's happening.
As I said, for example,
if you have the same stupid experience over
and over, that's a good sign that
something's occluding or skewing your vision,
probably something false.
So that's worth considering.
OK, so what happens here?
This is the simplest story or frame of reference.
That's another way of thinking about it.
This is how you frame the world.
Wherever you are, you're aiming at something.
As you sit here,
for example, maybe you're aiming
at the information that you're acquiring,
but maybe as you get tired, you're thinking, well,
your vision will shift
a bit; it's time for a break.
So the underlying motivational systems will
shift your goal, but they shift your
whole frame of perceptual reference.
So for example, if you're hungry and you go
into the kitchen, the kitchen makes itself
manifest as a place to make something to eat.
You ignore everything.
You're not going to be concerned
with the decor if you're hungry.
Because you can imagine walking into your
kitchen and looking at it like a design problem.
But normally, when you walk into your kitchen,
you walk in there under the influence of hunger.
And so the kitchen is a place to provide food.
And so what you see are all the things relevant to
that or all the things that will get in the way.
And I mean this literally.
That's how motivation transforms perception.
You don't see valueless facts and
apply a system of value to them.
Your motivational systems
set up your perceptions for you
so that what you see in the world essentially are
tools that will move you forward,
pathways that you can walk on, and obstacles that
are in your way, and everything else is invisible.
So one of the things you'll see, for example,
if you want to set up a given room in a manner
that makes you feel welcome,
one of the things you can do is figure out what
you do there, like what actions
do you undertake in the room?
And then you want to put everything in the room
in a place that makes those actions
the least amount of trouble.
If there's a place you walk down continually,
you don't want it cluttered so
that there's even any visual clutter there,
because if it's a place you walk down habitually
and there's visual clutter,
when you see the clutter, you'll see the clutter
as an obstacle, and it will annoy you.
And you can actually do this in a room.
It's quite fun if you're
trying to fix up your room.
You sit in your bed and you can think,
"What in this room annoys me?"
Right, right.
And then you can see.
You'll see, as soon as you orient yourself
in that direction, you'll think, "Well,
that's not put in the right place,
and I'm always bumping into that,
and I never seem to clean up that corner."
And you can fix all that.
And what you're doing is,
you're organizing your environment so
that the pathways are clear,
so the obstacles are cleared away,
and so the things that facilitate
your progress forward are at hand.
So, for example, if you—that's why, in
my first book, I
talked about people about—what was the rule?
Clean up your room before you criticize the world.
Well, so maybe you want to organize your closet.
That's a pain.
It's like, take all your clothes out,
figure out which ones fit you.
That's probably annoying because you're
not the man you once were, right?
So you have to throw away all those clothes
that only fit the hypothetical you from yesterday.
And you have to make complex decisions
about what's appropriate, what isn't.
You have to figure out what the hell your clothes
are for and what image—they're
tools to maneuver in the world.
And you have to figure out what they're
for and what you're trying to attain by wearing
them, and if they're of reasonable quality,
and every single piece of clothing has to have
that decision tree associated with it,
or the piece of clothing will be
foreign to you and you won't like it.
You won't even take it off the hanger,
and then you have to organize your closet
so it's not annoying when you open it.
It's actually a very complicated thing to do,
because if you do it right,
you put all your clothing in order,
in relationship to your aspirations.
So there's actually no way of organizing your
closet properly without arranging
your aspirations properly.
And so that's why you can start in a low place.
It's like, well, my closet's a mess, and I don't
get a big pat on the back for setting it straight.
It's harder than you think to do it perfectly.
And you should do it so that when you open your
closet, you think,
"Well, that looks like a civilized person lives
here," and so that all the things that are
there are things that you would hypothetically
wear, or maybe would aspire to wear,
and that nothing is in there that shouldn't be
in there, which requires a very
differentiating judgment.
Lots of people, you see this when they get older,
their whole house is so damn cluttered,
they just can't do anything with it.
And it's a nightmare being in a house like
that because there's 150,000 decisions
that haven't been made.
To go there and clean up,
I've done that with my clients.
It's like, you try to move one thing and they
have, "No, that was my great aunt's from 1860."
It's like, "Yeah, but you haven't looked at it
for 30 years, and it's in a box in your kitchen,
and it's been there for a decade."
It's like, "Well, we can't do any—mom will
be very upset if we do anything with that."
It's like, yeah, that and the other
50,000 things in the house.
Every single one of those
cluttered items is a fight that no one had.
The whole house is just full of that.
It's horrible.
And your closet is probably a little nightmare
like that, 300 decisions you don't want to make.
And maybe you can't face the whole closet.
It's like, fine, fix up one foot of it.
But it's so interesting to do it as a meditative
exercise, especially if
you take the time to do it.
Put six pieces of clothing on the bed.
Maybe that's enough and think, OK,
who bought these?
And what were they aiming at?
And is this what I want?
And what for?
And that forces you to start
the process of envisioning.
So all of these little micro stories that your
instincts pop up for you,
and what you're trying to do as you mature is
to integrate them into something approximating a
maximally desirable character.
And so that's not just an internal process.
It's not merely a matter of getting your act
together because people say that,
"Get your act together."
It's like, no, you're not getting your act
together exactly, because there's you,
there's your husband, and there's your family, and
there's your community, and there's your state.
And there's a lot more to you than
the you that has to get its act together.
You have to establish harmonious relationships up
all of those levels of hierarchy.
There's no mental health
that's just inside your head.
That's not a reasonable way
of looking at the world.
You're not going to be mentally healthy
unless you can get along with other people.
You think, "How deep is this?"
The worst people are psychopathic criminals.
Let's say that.
Maybe they're not the worst.
They're up there, though.
And you can take the worst psychopathic criminals,
so the people who treat other people
and themselves with the utmost contempt,
and how do you punish them?
By putting them in solitary confinement.
That's how social people are.
You can take the worst antisocial person
and punish them by isolating them.
And you're not the worst antisocial person.
So you imagine how important being properly
embedded in the social environment is to you.
There's no getting your act together without
working that at multiple
levels of social existence.
There's no being sane in a toxic relationship.
That's not going to happen.
You've got to drop the idea.
Part of the reason that you want to treat other
people the way you would want to be treated is
because there's no difference between the two.
So, for example,
if you establish—let's say you go out of your way
to be of service to other people,
and you might contrast that with being selfish.
OK, but what's the consequence of that?
Let's think it through for a minute.
There's only one of you.
There's a lot of other people.
OK, so now imagine you're running around,
trying to make yourself the most
useful possible to other people.
OK, and you do that for, like, 1,000 people.
Well, 900 of those people are going
to be heavily inclined to reciprocate.
So now you've put yourself in a position where
there's only one of you, and there's 900 people
trying to do for you what you've done for them.
That's a good deal.
When your kids, when they're teenagers,
they're striving to be popular.
That's not exactly what they're striving for.
And popularity isn't some sort of shallow virtue.
It's like, if your kids can be of proper service
to their peers, they're going to be surrounded
by people who are thrilled to have them around.
Yeah, well, if you were surrounded all the time
by people who are thrilled to have you around,
you wouldn't have to be worried
about your mental health.
That'd pretty much take care of itself.
There is a corollary to that.
When psychologists started to investigate
the structure of self-definitional
descriptors, self-definitional adjectives—sad,
happy, dutiful, creative—they
noticed that they clumped in bin.
So if you're happy, you're
more likely to be talkative.
If you're angry, you're more likely to be sad.
If you're creative, you're more
likely to be interested in ideas.
If you're dutiful, you're
more likely to be patriotic.
Things clump.
Self-consciousness clumps with misery,
right, so tightly in the NEO-PI-R,
which is a five-dimensional personality inventory,
one of the canonical inventories,
one of the facets of neuroticism,
which is the proclivity for negative emotion,
they all clump, the negative emotions,
is self-consciousness.
So here's the situation.
The more you think about your narrow self,
the more miserable you are.
And it's not causal, exactly.
They're not distinguishable from one another.
There's no difference between being
hyper-concerned with your immediate self
and being miserable.
Now, you might ask, "What's the way out of that?"
And you might say, "Well,
stop thinking about yourself."
And if I tell you to stop thinking about
yourself and you try that, you're just going to
think about yourself not thinking about yourself.
And so you're going to be
thinking about yourself nonstop.
It doesn't work.
One of the things you can do with socially anxious
people, this is a good thing to know,
a practical tip.
If you're anxious at parties,
you're worried about how other people are reacting
to you, start trying to make them comfortable.
Forget about you.
But don't forget about you
the way, like, consciously.
Focus on the other people and think, "OK,
how could I make this person feel
as welcome as possible right now?"
Listening to people,
by the way, that really works.
You can ask people questions.
There's so many people out there
that never get listened to.
If you can listen 10% better than the typical
person, you'll be so popular,
you won't be able to stand it.
So you could just start with—"I
don't have anything to say."
It's like, that's OK.
Ask stupid questions and listen.
People will be so happy,
they'll just talk you to death.
OK, so your instincts, your basic motivations
grip this whole perceptual frame.
They establish the aim, but they determine
what you see and how you feel about it.
I'll show you how that works here.
OK, so you're in one of these frames.
What do you see in the world?
You're hungry.
Well, you're happy to see a butter knife.
You're happy to see a loaf of bread.
Those are tools that will enable you to fulfill
the demand of the frame.
When you go into the kitchen,
your perception will narrow so that all you see
are the facilitators of your desire
and the obstacles.
The facilitators will fill you with positive
emotion, and the obstacles will
fill you with negative emotion.
That's how you evaluate the world.
You have a frame
that sets up the perceptual objects.
The frame has a goal and a starting point.
The starting point is where you are.
The goal is where you want to be,
in hand with a peanut butter sandwich.
That's your goal.
And then maybe your kid comes in and wants
to show you a picture and you're annoyed.
And why?
It's because you're trying to make
a damn peanut butter sandwich.
And so under normal circumstances,
maybe you'd be happy about that.
But because you're hungry and irritable,
the child's offering appears as
an obstacle and elicits negative emotion.
So it's very useful to know that.
You don't see the world as objects
and lay a structure value on it.
The world presents itself to you as pathways,
tools, and obstacles,
and then everything else that's invisible,
which is like 99.9% of everything.
And then you understand emotions as soon as
you understand that, which is also quite fun.
OK, so you go from point A to point B.
You're always doing that as long
as you're awake and conscious.
You're always on a journey somewhere,
micro journey maybe.
And you're always looking for things that will get
you to where you're going and things
that will get in your way.
The things that will get you to where you're
going, they fill you with positive emotion.
Two kinds of positive emotion.
There's the kind of emotion that emerges
when you get what you're after.
That's satiation.
So you eat a peanut butter sandwich,
you're satisfied.
The price you pay for that is the little frame you
were operating in that gives
your life purpose disappears.
So on graduation day at high school,
you're king of the castle,
and the next day, you're, like, cap in hand,
beggar, looking for a job at Starbucks.
But you see what I mean?
So you attain something,
and that is satisfying, but the price you pay
for that, it blows out the frame of reference.
It brings it to an end.
That's what satiation does,
and that's a particular kind of positive emotion.
The positive emotion that you
run on is more like hope.
The thing that makes us exhilarated or
enthusiastic or interested or curious or motivated
is the vision that we're
moving towards a valued goal.
OK, so now you've got to think about
that because there's corollaries.
The positive emotion that fills your life
with enthusiasm and hope is experienced
in relationship to a goal,
not as a consequence of its accomplishment.
OK, so the corollary is you should have a goal.
Another corollary is you should have
a goal that you can take steps towards.
Because if the goal is so damn impossible that
you can't take steps towards it, then the world
just lays itself out as a series of obstacles.
So if your goal is so stellar that you can't
move towards it, you should lower your goal.
You've bitten off more than you can chew.
And this is what you do with little kids.
If you want to encourage them to do something,
you set them a goal that's
within their domain of achievement,
but slightly difficult,
so that they can move towards it,
but it demands a bit, and they transform
themselves as they're pursuing it.
So a goal that you'll find optimally
meaningful will do two things.
It'll beckon to you.
You want to achieve it.
It'll produce positive emotion because
you can see yourself making movement.
But it'll be movement that pushes you
to transform, so that the next
goal that you chase will be better.
So that's another thing, why you don't have
to worry too much about what you're aiming at.
You do the best job you can.
What do you want?
OK, this is what I want.
Are you right?
You don't know, because what do you know?
But you decide to pursue it.
Then you break it down, so you have a name
that you could hypothetically move towards.
OK,
now you move towards it and you start to change
a little bit because of what you're learning.
OK, at some point, you're
going to change the goal.
So you can hold the goal
with something like a light touch,
knowing that it's not final, but also knowing that
even though it's not final, you should pursue it.
So, just like there's lots of pathways
into chaos—all you have to do is confront
something that's an impediment, it doesn't matter
what it is—there's a lot of pathways uphill.
So uphill is a particular direction,
but there's many entry points.
And as you enter one of those entry points and you
transform, you'll converge
on the proper goal across time.
You're going like this, error,
but it'll correct as you move forward.
So one of the things my clients used to ask me,
students, too, is, "I don't know what to do."
Well, then they'd be like that for 15 years.
"I never figured out what I should do."
Well, one thing you're doing is getting older.
Right, so there's no zero-cost stasis.
So if you're not moving ahead,
you are degenerating.
OK, so there's no staying where you are,
so then, you don't know what to do.
It's like, well, guess.
Let's see if we can come up with something that's
slightly better than whatever
the hell it is that you're doing.
We'll talk about this in more detail tomorrow,
about how you can get that ball rolling.
And you might think, well, "I don't want
to take the risk of aiming at the wrong thing."
It's like, you're going to aim at the wrong
thing, because what the hell do you know?
But if you aim at the wrong thing and you
practice, your aim will get better.
So don't worry about that too much.
It's like, pick something.
Pick some interesting disciplinary routine.
Now, this is a place where moral
relativism actually has its role.
You might say, well, there's a variety
of different forms of acceptable morality.
And obviously that's true,
because we each have a different personality.
So there's a fair bit of play in the moral system.
That doesn't mean it isn't oriented
toward something that's stellar.
What it means is, there's lots of games
that you can play that will work.
But the one game that doesn't work is no game,
because there's no progress there.
There's no discipline, there's no calling,
there's no orientation, there's no transformation.
Pick something.
If you do nothing, first of all, you can't.
Let's just try it.
You can't do nothing.
You're going to think,
you're going to fantasize, maybe bitterly.
There's literally no doing nothing.
All you're doing when you're doing nothing
is allowing yourself to fall under the sway
of the most narrow and bitter visions
that can possibly inhabit you.
Yeah, well, that's a really
stupid strategy, obviously.
So, pick something.
What we'll see tomorrow—here's
a practical solution.
OK, you don't know what to do.
Well, what do people do, broadly speaking?
It's like, do you have a relationship?
Well, no.
OK, well, most people want one.
You probably do, too.
So even if you don't know you
want one, we could try that.
Do you have any friends?
Do you have any family?
Are you pursuing anything educational?
Do you have any job?
Is there any way you're making
yourself useful to other people?
Do you have any interests at all outside of work?
Et cetera.
We'll go through this in detail.
And if you don't know what to do, it's like,
well, try part of one of those things and see.
Maybe you're one of those people
who just doesn't need anyone else.
You're not, because no one is,
but maybe you think that.
We could at least put it to the test and see.
Probably you want a friend, and maybe you're
introverted, so you want one friend, but not zero.
And so, if you don't know what to do,
nothing is the wrong solution.
And you can look and see what
other people do and try to do that.
And that's partly why, by the way, when you're
a teenager, it matters to you so much to fit in.
It's not like you're fitting in.
That's such an insane way—you know, "If
your friends jumped over a cliff,
would you jump off, too?"
It's like, well, probably.
Maybe it means there's a bear chasing us.
You never know.
It's like, of course,
teenagers try to fit in because they're
trying to socialize themselves into the group.
They're trying to escape from their parents
and their dependency, and they do
that by making a group affiliation.
Now, you can tell your kids, "Don't sell your
soul so that you're a member of the group."
That's a whole different discussion because
you don't want to pretend that you're
something that you're not.
You don't want to sacrifice the possibility
of your higher-order being to idiot
identification with the whim of the crowd.
But that's not the same thing as, "It shouldn't
matter to you what your friends think."
You know what sort of person it
doesn't matter to what other people think?
That's a psychopath.
And most of the time, you should be damn
concerned with what other people think.
Not always, and that's a tight discrimination.
But most of the time, if most people think there's
something wrong with you, they're probably right.
Sometimes they're not.
And that's an edge case.
All right.
Another way of looking at emotions.
You move from the present to the future.
There are things that you predict
that are going the way you want them to.
That fills you with positive emotion.
And then there's a category of obstacle—we'll talk
about this tomorrow—there's a category
of obstacle that's unpredictable.
Sometimes you'll run into obstacles that you know
how to move,
and sometimes you'll run into obstacles
whose nature you don't understand
and you can't predict.
You run into something you don't
understand about your husband, for example.
It's a bottomless mystery,
and we'll talk about that a little bit tomorrow.
So, three categories of
stimuli that you respond to emotionally.
Things that get you on your way,
things that get in your way,
and things you don't understand.
And the things you don't understand,
that's a bottomless pit.
That's a hole.
We'll talk about that tomorrow.
OK, I'll close with this one today.
I showed you one of these
little story frames, right?
You're here.
That's the present.
You're aiming at something.
The world orients itself so
that there are pathways forward to that.
You want the pathway because otherwise your
plan is invalidated or you'll be upset.
You don't want too many obstacles.
You want things to help you along your way.
That's the world.
You're always in a little frame like that.
OK, those frames are nested,
and that nesting is your identity.
When you're developing a vision,
you're developing the entire nested structure.
OK, so I'll show you how that works.
OK, your identity is not something
you carry around in your head.
OK, so now you're two and you have all these
motivational forces working within you.
OK, as you mature, you integrate them,
and you integrate them in a way that makes you
a good player within the family
and then within your friends.
So you integrate those instincts
in an increasingly social environment.
And then as you mature more, you
get better and better at doing that,
across longer and longer spans of time, in more
and more situations with more and more people.
OK, so let's break that down.
This will show you how you move from the abstract
moral imperative to the particular.
So let's say you tell your child to make dinner,
and he's three.
So he looks at you.
"What do you mean?"
And you give him a cuff because
he's too stupid to make dinner.
This is not a good plan.
And so what's your problem?
The problem is he's three.
OK, so why is that a problem?
And the problem is he doesn't know
what complete, make dinner means.
He doesn't know the micro steps.
When you say to someone, "Make dinner,"
you're assuming that they know how to make dinner.
You're assuming that they've been socialized
the same way you have been, so that when you
utter that phrase, they understand what it means.
OK, so we decompose that.
What does it mean to make dinner?
So my son's 15 months old,
and he's starting to learn to set the table.
But you can't say "set the table,"
partly because he can't even see the table.
It's here and he's this high.
But you can say,
"Do you know where the knife drawer is?"
He'll go, "Yes."
Say, "Go to the knife drawer."
He goes to the knife drawer.
"Pull the knife drawer open.
Feel around till you feel a knife."
He'll do that.
You can give him a pat on the head.
"Good work.
Got the knife?"
"Yes."
"Take the knife into the table
and put it on the top of the table."
OK, so what has he done?
He's started to set the table.
You see, you've broken it down, right?
And you've broken it down
to implementable subroutines.
So, setting the table is an integrated story.
It's part of an identity.
It's an integrated story that involves
a variety of mastered subroutines.
Part of what you're doing when you're learning
a new task is you have to break the task down
to the level of subroutine
that you need to master.
Right, and so when you're training someone,
the first thing you have to find out is,
well, what don't they know?
Maybe you're training
someone for customer service.
It's like, maybe they whisper on the phone.
You might want to find that out.
Do you know how to talk?
You might assume yes,
and that assumption might be completely wrong.
Maybe they have to triple
the volume of their voice.
You have to play until you find out at what
level of the subroutines the person is lacking.
That includes you, and you
build it from the bottom up.
So it's cut vegetables, set table, do dishes.
OK, that's part of completing a meal.
Now, if you're a halfway civilized five-year-old,
maybe you can make a basic meal.
So then you can say to your five-year-old,
"You know how to make some Kraft dinner?"
And they've got that.
They know where the pots are,
they know how to boil water.
So you can now tag that whole complex
small subpersonality with a single
verbal tag, and they can do it.
OK, so maybe if you're a good father,
you know how to make a meal,
you know how to play with the baby.
And what do you do when you play with the baby?
Well, you play peekaboo,
you tickle the baby, you clean the baby.
Those are subroutines.
Now you know how to take care of the baby,
and you know how to make a meal.
And so maybe that's part of being a good parent.
And that's part of what makes you a good partner.
And that's part of what makes you a good person.
And you can say to your wife, "Be a good person."
It's like, maybe you tell
your kids that, "Be good."
And sometimes they sort of know what you mean,
but you probably have to decompose that down
the hierarchy of identity till you hit the level
at which they're insufficient and repair that.
Imagine you're playing the piano,
playing a complex melody, and you trip
over a note, and you do that repeatedly.
So what you do is, you slow down,
and then you concentrate on the place where you
made a mistake, and then you see what you're doing
when you make the mistake,
and then you adjust that,
and then you practice the adjustment till you've
automated it, then you integrate it in the rhythm,
then you play the whole phrase,
and then you go over it.
That's exactly what you do when you're
trying to solve a problem of adaptation.
You hit an obstacle,
you decompose it down the hierarchy
of specialization till you see where the error is,
the minimal error, rectify that, practice
the rectification, and then sequence back up.
And then you're aiming always up.
When you're training your two-year-old to put
a butter knife on the table,
it's a subset of helping him become a good person.
But that good person isn't some
disembodied abstraction.
It's the integrated hierarchy of a set of leveled
specializations all aiming in the same direction.
I'll close with this.
Here's a way of conceptualizing that.
Let's say you have a highly skilled athlete
on your team who's also elected by
his peers to be the captain of the team
because of his leadership abilities.
OK, so then you can imagine
what athlete means in that context.
It means, let's say, possibly,
he's the most skilled player on the team.
But what do you mean skilled?
Well, maybe he can score the most goals,
but that's not sufficient, right?
He needs to score the most goals in a way
that motivates everyone else on the team
to score the most goals themselves and to improve
in their capacity to do that over time and not
to be jealous of the differences in skill
at the team level and to get along in a way
that makes the entire enterprise
worth replicating over and over.
And so if you do that, well,
then you're a skilled athlete.
And that's the same in the broader moral domain,
is you want to be skilled
at the specific things that you do.
You want to have the perceptions and the actions
at hand that enable you to do that.
But you want to have them integrated
into a personality that makes all of the games
that you're playing work in a broader game
and work repetitively with other
people in a self-improving direction.
If you do that, your life will be meaningful,
because meaning is the instinct
that tells you that you're doing that.
It's not some metaphysical abstraction that you
can eradicate with, like,
a nihilistic rationalism.
"What's the point of life?"
It's an experiential reality.
It means that you're existing in harmony with your
integration towards the highest possible purpose.
That's a good way of thinking about.
Your conscience will aid you in that,
and so will the manifestation of your interests.
OK, tomorrow, we'll talk about how to make
that concrete, to bring it all the way
down to Earth, because you can do that.
You can and you need to.
All right.
Thank you very much.